Records of the Bible Translation and Utilization Program, NCCCUSA
Yale University Divinity School Library
Records of the Bible Translation and Utilization Program, NCCUSA
1980-1999
RG 218
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
This collection contains unofficial archival documentation of the work of the Bible Translation and Utilization Program of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A., which was the policy-making body for the New Revised Standard Version of the Bible. The records date primarily from the period when the donor, Dr. J. Shannon Clarkson, was a BTU member. They document the preparation, launch, and promotion of the NRSV and reactions to it.
National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America. Bible Translation and Utilization
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of J. Shannon Clarkson, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
In 1980 the Division of Education and Ministry of the National Council of Churches in the U.S.A. authorized the translation committee of the Revised Standard Version of the Bible to begin working on a new translation. The Bible Translation and Utilization group (variously known as Program Ministry, Department, Unit, Committee, Section, and Program) was the policy-making body for the New Revised Standard Version, which was launched on September 30, 1990. During the period documented by these files, the BTU unit was directed by Arthur O. Van Eck and David J. Lull. BTU members represented various denominational groups; Dr. J. Shannon Clarkson, who donated these records, represented the United Church of Christ. Dr. Bruce Metzger, who was also involved with the preparation of the Revised Standard Version, was a member of the BTU group. The BTU was responsible for overseeing the development of an accurate translation of the Bible, developing contracts with publishers, developing plans for the utilization of the translation, and working with church bodies to integrate the translation into curricula, worship resources, evangelism resources, etc.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains unofficial archival documentation of the work of the Bible Translation and Utilization Program of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A., the policy-making body for the New Revised Standard Version. The records were collected by Dr. Shannon Clarkson and date primarily from the period 1988 to 1999 when she was a BTU member and/or Chairperson. They document the preparation, launch, and promotion of the NRSV and related products. The collection complements the documentation held in Yale Divinity Library Record Group No. 70, Records of the Standard Bible Committee. The Standard Bible Committee was responsible for preparation of the Revised Standard Version of the Bible.
Series I, Correspondence, consists primarily of letters exchanged between Shannon Clarkson and BTU representatives or copies of correspondence between publishers and scholars and BTU representatives. Issues addressed include the structure and policy of the BTU, critiques of the NRSV translation, publishing and distribution rights for the NRSV and related products, promotion/marketing, and plans for consultations.
Series II, Policy, includes background documents regarding the BTU program and regarding the marketing and distribution of the NRSV and related products. Series III, Agendas and Minutes, documents meetings of the BTU group and plans for consultations that it sponsored, including on "Biblical Interpretation Beyond Patriarchy" (1993), "Biblical Literacy" (1994), and "Next Steps in Translation" (1999: The Authority of Religious Traditions for Bible Translation; 2000: Ideologies of Biblical Texts and English Bible Translations).. Series IV, Operations, includes contracts with publishers of the NRSV and related products, and budget information. Series V, Promotion, includes reports on promotion activities, publicity publications, copies of "The Latest Word - A newsletters for those who are helping to launch the New Revised Standard Version of the Bible", and endorsements and critiques of the NRSV.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1988-1999
II. Policy, 1980-1994
III. Agendas and Minutes, 1989-1999
IV. Operations, 1988-1999
V. Promotion, 1989-1995
VI. Collected Material, 1989-1999
Bible -- Translating; Bible -- Versions; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America. Bible Translation and Utilization
- Correspondence, 1988-1999; Series I
  - Including to/from Rev. Arthur O. Van Eck; Dr. Shannon Clarkson; Randall Bailey; Bruce Metzger; others, 1988 Dec- 1990 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Van Eck, Clarkson, 1991 Jan- 1991 Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Franklin Electronics; Zondervan Pub; to other publishers, 1991 Apr-1991 Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Van Eck; Clarkson; Gordon Conwell Seminary, 1991 Jul- 1991 Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Van Eck; Jean Lebkind; Oxford U Press; Thomas Nelson Pub.; Princton Seminary, 1992 Feb- 1992 Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Van Eck; Johnnie Godwin; Scott Tunseth, 1992 Jul- Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Van Eck; Godwin; John Kohlenberger, 1993 Feb- Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Powell; Abingdon Press; Van Eck; Broadman; Holmes Pub.; Zondervan, 1993 Aug- Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - R. Bailey; Van Eck; Carol Fouke; L.N. Thurber, 1194 Jan- Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Godwin; Van Eck; Thomas Nelson Pub., 1994 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - United Methodist Pub Hs; VanEck; Oxford University Press, 1994 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clarkson; Van Eck; Broadman Holman Press, 1994 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Van Eck; United Methodist Pub. Hs; Broadman Holman Press; Moravian Theological Seminary; Augsburg Fortress Press, 1995 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oxford University Press; Clarkson; Van Eck, 1995 Apr-Jul (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Colorado Christian Consultants; Van Eck; Princeton Seminary; United Methodist Publishers Hs; Clarkson, 1995 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - United Methodist Publishers Hs; Van Eck; Clarkson; Whitman; Breed Abbot and Morgan; David Lull, 1996 Jan- 1998 Dec (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - David J. Lull; Clarkson, 1999 Feb-Apr (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Next Steps in Bible Translation Applications: A-M, 1999 May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Next Steps in Bible Translation Applications: P-W, 1999 May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lull; Clarkson; S H Ringe; Lyn Oslek (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lull; Clarkson; Verdi West, 1999 Aug- Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clarkson; Lull; Boyarin; Jensen, 1999 Oct 20-29 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clarkson; Boyarin; Halpern, 1999 Nov (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Policy, 1980-1994; Series II
  - Report of Task Force on Issues of Biblical Translation; Background documents for NRSV; Specifications for NRSV; Proposal for Consultation on Feminist Biblical Translation Issues; NRSV Translation Development Plan, 1980, 1991 Dec-1994 Aug (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Provisional Standing Rules for BTU, 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Policy on decision making, 1994 Apr-Nov (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Privilege of Quotation, 1987 Apr- 1991 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Marketing and promotion, 1993 Feb- 1994 Aug (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Guide for preparing position description, including membership lists, 1990 Mar (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Agendas and Minutes, 1989-1999; Series III
  - Meetings in New York City; Marco Island, FL., 1989 Arp- 1990 Nov (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - NRSV update; New launch phase II; meeting in Florida, 1991 Jul- Nov (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Database report; meetings in FL and NJ, 1992 Mar- 1993 Apr (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Minutes: Biblical Literacy Team; Transition and Coordination Comm.; The Future of Feminist Interpretation of Bible; flyer from consultation on "Biblical Interpretation Beyond Patriarchy", 1993 Jun- Oct (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Meeting in Marco Island FL., 1993 Nov (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Meeting in N.J., 1994 Apr- May (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Promotion concerns; Minutes search committee; meeting in FL., 1994 Aug- 1994 Nov (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Meeting in PA.; meeting in Chicago; Search committee for new director, 1994 Nov- Dec (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Meeting in N.J.; meeting in FL, 1995 Apr- Nov (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Consultation on Next Steps in Translation, 1997 Jun-Nov (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - BTU Committee meeting; BTU goals; Next Steps consultation 2000, 1999 Nov (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Operations, 1988-1999; Series IV
  - Marketing
    - List of publishers; Contract model, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Conference agenda on marketing; Sales trends; List of publishers with contracts; Budget information, 1992 Sep- 1994 Apr (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Budget Information
    - BTU operations and activities, 1990 Oct- 1993 Sep (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - BTU budget income and expenditures, 1993 Nov- 1994 Apr (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - BTU and Bible Fund budgets, 1994 Nov- 1996 Apr (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - BTU including proposed budget for 1999, 1998 Mar- 1999 Mar (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Promotion, 1989-1995; Series V
  - Helps for planning promotions, 1994-1995, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Publicity articles and ideas, 1990-1993, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Reports on promotion activity, etc., 1992-1993, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Articles; Endorsements; etc., 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Articles; Endorsements; etc., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Publicity and programs, incl. service to celebrate publication of NRSV held at Interchurch Center, litanies, 1990-1993, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Endorsements and critiques of NRSV, 1989-1995, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Brochures re. NRSV-related products, 1993, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Bookmarks; Brochures, including "God's Word for All the People: Why Women Welcome the New Revised Standard Version of the Bible." (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "The Latest Word" newsletter regarding NRSV, 1989-1994 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Phase II: summary of introduction of NRSV, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Collected Material, 1989-1999; Series VI
  - Magazine and newspaper articles, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
  - Ecumenical articles; Booklets; etc., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Newsletters; Misc. articles; Cartoons, 1989-1995, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ: Reports; Misc. articles, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ: General Assembly Booklet; 1998 proposed budget, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ: Connections newsletter; Misc. articles, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ: including Jubilee Quadrennium material, 1996, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65)